（制片：吉姆·克里格）
（制片：金珀莉·摩洛）
（编剧：提姆·谢里登）
（导演：克里斯·帕尔默）
（蝙蝠侠：漫长的万圣节 下）
告诉我这一切永远不会停止
Tell me this never has to end.
花开花谢  布鲁斯  但如果我们够幸运…
All things wither, Bruce, but if we're lucky...
就不会等太久
Not for a long time.
你是不是忘了什么？
Aren't you forgetting something?
又要签？
Again?
（资产转移  布鲁斯·韦恩）
（新持有人  卡麦·法尔康尼）
我无法抗拒你
I can't resist you.
没有男人抗拒得了我
No man can.
（情人节）
三月十七日
圣派翠克节
四月一日
你一直都很听话
You've been a good boy.
基金会对你还有我们来说
The foundation was such a burden to you,
是个重担…
to us...
整间公司都是
Just like the rest of the company.
（韦恩基金会股份转让书）
（卡麦·法尔康尼）
你知道你该做什么  这样我们才能在一起
You know what you have to do so we can be together.
韦恩先生  我想你对这株盆栽施太多肥了
Mr. Wayne, I think you've overfed your philodendron.
住手！
Stop!
这不是你  布鲁斯  她用了某种方法控制你
This isn't you, Bruce. She's controlling you somehow.
该死  抱歉了！
Oh, hell. Sorry!
噢
Oh.
你怎么知道的？
How did you know?
你又没有很低调
Well, you haven't exactly been discreet.
你和毒藤女公开出双入对  还把资产转让给罗马人
Appearing with Ivy in public and signing assets over to the Roman.
我去通知律师团  少爷
I'll wake the lawyers, sir.
警方马上就到
Police will be here any minute.
把你记得的部分告诉他们  然后上床休息
Tell them everything you remember and then get to bed.
你脸色很差
You look awful.
我说过  我不需要伙伴
I told you, I don't want a partner.
过去这三个月  你确实需要一位伙伴
You sure wanted one these past three months.
三个月？
Three months?
要杀得那绿油油的女人  措手不及  需要一点时间
It took a while to catch the jolly green jezebel with her guard down.
-假日杀手呢？  -还没抓到
- And holiday?  - Still at large.
（老钟茶馆）
吉尔达  抱歉  电影我们晚点再看
Gilda, I'm sorry. We'll make the late movie.
我很期待
I'm looking forward to it.
我想回家了
I think I'd like to go home.
为什么？我们可以…
Why? We can...
好吧  好吧
Yeah. Yeah, okay.
（员工办公室）
天啊！
Jesus!
（弹药）
哈维…
Harvey...
你说得对
You were right.
供应枪枝给假日杀手的人就是老钟
Chong's been supplying holiday with his guns.
你早该听我的  吉姆  早点锁定那家伙
You should have listened to me, Jim, moved on this guy sooner.
我们可能就能察觉什么
We might have learned something.
假日杀手正在隐匿行踪
The holiday killer's covering his tracks.
母亲节
Mother's day.
快要到了
This one snuck up on us.
是啊
Sure did.
我们的朋友呢？
Where's our friend?
（阿卡姆精神病院）
谁帮助你逃跑的？
Who helped you escape?
说出名字  否则我…
Give me a name or I'll...
是我母亲
It was my mother.
帮我的人就是她
That's who helped me.
我一年前勒死那个老巫婆
I strangled the old witch years ago,
但我想她还是会保佑帅气的小强尼的
but I think she still watches over handsome little jonny.
母亲节快乐
Happy mother's day.
开派对啰
Party time.
母亲
Mother.
走这里
Through here.
亲爱的  我不知道这是不是…
Sweetheart, I don't know if this is the...
你想拿什么就拿去
Take what you want.
别伤害我们
Don't hurt us.
他没事吧？
Is he okay?
谁在乎啊  走吧
I don't care. Let's go.
布鲁斯  你在做什么？
Bruce, what are you doing?
妈妈？
Mother?
我得带你回家
We have to get you home.
布鲁斯！
Bruce!
她在哪里  阿福？
Where is she, Alfred?
-她？ -我妈妈
- She?  - My mother.
我本来跟我妈妈在一起
I was with my mother.
先进来吧
Up we go.
警方正在搜寻昨晚
Gotham police are searching for two inmates
从阿卡姆精神病院逃逸的两名囚犯
that escaped from arkham asylum last night.
其中一名是强纳森·克莱恩博士  也就是稻草人…
One of them, Dr. Jonathan crane, aka the scarecrow...
从阿卡姆精神病院偷走了马匹
Stole one of arkham's horses from the grounds.
他被认为是极为危险的人物
He's considered extremely dangerous.
任何有他下落的民众
Anyone with knowledge of his whereabouts
请马上致电高谭市警局的专线
needs to call the Gotham pd hotline right away.
再次提醒  他被认为是极为危险的人物…
Again, he's considered highly dangerous...
等等
Wait.
我帮你准备了午餐
I packed your lunch.
谢谢  我得走了
Thanks. I gotta go.
我来看我父亲
I've come to see my father.
这是领带
It's a tie.
没错  我的假释官知道我来这里
And, yes, my parole officer knows I'm here.
苏菲亚  我的小女儿
Sofia, my little girl.
楼下的警察有为难你吗？
Heat give you any trouble downstairs?
警察来得比十年前还多呢
There's more cops here than I ever saw in ten years on the inside.
那是“假日小组”  据他们说  是来保护我的
"Holiday detail." For my protection, or so they tell me.
-听着  我很忙  所以…  -所以我必须跟你谈谈
- Listen, I'm very busy, so...  - That's why I need to talk to you.
爸爸  我想加入领导核心
Papa, I want to be in the room.
苏菲亚  我们谈过了…
Sofia, we have already discussed...
我照你说的让克莱恩逃了
I executed the crane escape like you ordered.
这场和萨尔·马洛尼之间  愚蠢的战争
And this foolish war with sal maroni,
-我认为…  -够了！
- I think...  - Basta!
眼下情势…有些紧张
Things... are strained.
我们一半的成员都被假日杀手或马洛尼干掉了
Half our top earners have been taken out by either holiday or maroni.
我们本来能指望韦恩
We had a chance with Wayne,
但他现在不管事了  我们必须重新改组
but now that he's out, we have to restructure.
所以你更需要我啊
That is exactly why you need me.
我不需要
I do not.
苏菲亚  如果我让你加入
Sofia, if I bring you in now,
新的合作者会以为我正在安排继任者
our new earners will think I am lining up a successor.
那会让我看起来很老气…  和软弱
And that will make me look old...  And weak.
你既不老气也不会没用
You are neither.
但也帮不上忙
Nevertheless.
很好  讨论结束
Good. End of discussion.
去购物吧
Now go buy someting.
大的  闪亮的  礼服  车子
Big, flashy. A dress, a car.
什么都可以  确保让大家都看得到
I don't care. Just make sure everybody sees it.
父亲节快乐  爸爸
Happy father's day, papa.
（惊天大劫案）
很遗憾高谭第一银行发生这种事
Awful business at first Gotham.
你怎么知道是稻草人干的？
How do you know it was the scarecrow?
克莱恩最近刚从阿卡姆逃跑
Crane recently fled arkham.
受害者身上的气体都是他的恐惧神经毒素
Gases all of his victims with a fear-inducing neurotoxin, so...
是啊  绝对就是他
Yeah, you can't really miss him.
所以  韦恩先生…
Look, so, Mr. Wayne...
叫我布鲁斯吧
Uh, it's Bruce.
两位要喝点什么吗？  阿福会调很棒的迈泰调酒
Can I get you anything? Alfred makes a terrific Mai Tai.
现在是早上八点半…
It's 8:30 in the...
不用了  谢谢
No. No, thank you.
关于除夕夜  我们有些问题想问你
We have some questions about new year's Eve.
阿尔贝托·法尔康尼在当晚被杀害
The night Alberto Falcone was murdered.
哈维整理线索后发现
Harvey here was updating the files,
你似乎是当晚游艇上
and it seems that you were the only passenger on that yacht
唯一还没提供证词的乘客
who didn't give us a statement.
恐怕我帮不上忙
Afraid I'm not much help.
我在游艇出事前就离开派对了
I left the party before all the commotion in a dinghy.
你们可能以为我失踪了
You probably noticed it was missing.
当然  若我在场就会提供证词
Of course, I'd have given you a statement anyway,
但那么做这件事就会登上媒体
except that it would have been a matter of public record
他们会把我的名字
and could place my name
与那天和我有约的小姐的名字刊在一起
next to that of the young lady I went to meet.
我认为她丈夫不是很喜欢我
I don't think her husband likes me very much.
还真刚好啊
That's very convenient.
对她老公来说并不是
Well, not for her husband.
以下是我想了解的部分
Here's what I'm trying to understand.
你最近将你产业中大片区域
You recently signed over significant areas of your business
转让给了卡麦·法尔康尼
to carmine Falcone.
那些都撤销了
That's all been reversed.
我当时被下药控制 如果你是指这个
你父亲和罗马人合作生意的时候
Was your father drugged and manipulated
也是被下药控制吗？
when he went into business with the Roman?
你很清楚
You know everything that monster is today
一手打造那头怪物的人就是韦恩…
was born of the legitimacy handed him by the name Wayne...
哈维
Harvey.
没关系
It's all right.
没错  我父亲和法尔康尼合盖了不少医院
Yes, my father built hospitals with Falcone.
但驱使他这么做的
But the only influence he was under
只有拯救无辜生命的强烈欲望
was an overwhelming desire to save innocent lives.
那么他最后用多少条人命换取这个结果？
And how many other innocent lives did he end up trading for it?
据我所知…两条
Two... that I know of.
请救救我儿子
Please help my son.
我没有别的地方能去了
I have nowhere else to go.
往这走
This way. Over here.
放到桌上
Onto the desk.
目测胸口有四个…  不  五个枪伤
Looks like four... No, five bullet wounds to the chest.
你不该来这里  你儿子应该去医院
You shouldn't have come here. Your son needs to be in a hospital.
好让路易吉·马洛尼  去干掉他吗？
Where Luigi maroni could find him and finish the job?
不  韦恩医生  求求你
No, Dr. Wayne, please.
卡麦是我的独子
Carmine is my only son.
我会尽我所能
I'll do what I can.
-阿福  拿我的手术用具来  -马上来  主人
- Alfred, get my bag.  - Right away, sir.
他的情况稳定了  但我还不打算移动他
He's stable, but I don't want to move him yet.
谢谢  你的恩情我难以报答
Grazie. I can never repay you.
他还没脱离险境
He isn't out of the woods.
走吧  得让他好好休息
Come on, we have to let him rest.
你不该待在这里
You shouldn't be here.
没关系
It's okay.
你知道我爸是谁吗？
Do you know who my father is?
罗马人？
The Roman?
聪明的小子
Smart kid.
那你知道我会变成什么人吗？
So you know who I'm going to be?
罗马人
The Roman.
真聪明
Very smart.
你让我想起我的儿子
You remind me of my boy.
你父亲救了我一命
Your pop saved my life.
我想我们就是一家人了
I guess that makes us family.
这从你的口袋掉出来
It fell out of your pocket.
这是我的保险
My insurance policy.
外面有很多坏人
There's a lot of bad people out there.
罪犯
Criminals.
大家都知道罪犯很迷信
And everybody knows criminals are superstitious.
有时脱离困境
Sometimes all it takes to get out of a bad situation
只需要掷一枚硬币
is a good flip of the coin.
今天晚上对你没有用吗？
It didn't work for you tonight?
是啊
Yeah.
不过  人多力量大
Still, two heads are better than one.
不是吗？
No?
留着吧  孩子
Keep it, kid.
种什么因  得什么果
All we get is all we take.
托马斯·韦恩把路易吉·马洛尼的子弹
I was eight when Dr. Thomas Wayne pulled Luigi maroni's bullets
从法尔康尼胸口取出的时候  我八岁
out of Falcone's chest.
不到一年  我父亲便死于暴徒手下
My father was dead by a mobster's hand within a year.
我们家和罗马人之间的关系  也从那时就断了
Any connection between my family and the Roman died then, too.
谢谢两位来一趟  如果没别的事…
Thank you for stopping by. If there's nothing else...
先生们  上面写的名字和住址
Gentlemen, these are the names and addresses for those who can account
都和韦恩少爷那一晚的行踪有关
for master Wayne's whereabouts on the night in question.
上面的名字不少  那天晚上一定很盛大吧
A lot of names on here. Must have been quite a night.
是啊  有个男的被杀了
Yes, well, a man was murdered.
希望两位的单位能还给他
Let us hope your respective offices can deliver for him
当年托马斯和玛莎·韦恩得不到的正义
the justice still denied Thomas and Martha Wayne.
他们的遭遇是一场悲剧
What happened to them was a tragedy.
所以你的老板更该离法尔康尼这种人远一点
And all the more reason why your boss should stay away from men like Falcone.
能不能哪一天父亲的罪孽
Will there ever be a time when the sins of fathers
不需再靠他们的儿子来偿还？
don't fall to their sons for redemption?
再见
Good day.
他们会监视我今天所有行动
They're going to be watching my every move today
确认我不是凶手
to confirm that I'm not the killer.
所以你会待在家了？
Then you'll be staying in?
不  记得搞定不在场证明
No, just pay off some more alibis.
我得去工作了
I have to go to work.
坐好
Sit tight.
如果他知道我们两个的关系  他会气死的
If he knew about us, it would kill him.
我会待在这里  亲爱的
I'll be right here, love.
你最爱的西西里岛卷饼
Your favorite cannolis.
卷饼啊  Cannolo是1个cannoli是1盒
Cannoli. Cannolo for one, cannoli for a box.
你的意大利语好烂
Your Italian is sterco.
我知道  爸爸  抱歉
I know, papa. I'm sorry.
你在父亲节带西西里岛卷饼来  我原谅你了
You bring cannoli on father's day, I forgive.
坐吧
Sit.
所以…
So...
和法尔康尼的战争快烦死我们了  爸爸
This war with Falcone, it's killing us, pop.
卡麦认为我们和那个假日杀手有关系
Carmine thinks we've got something to do with this holiday jerk.
胡说八道
Sciocchezze.
卡麦的妄想症跟假日杀手无关
Carmine's paranoia is not to do with holiday
而是跟新任检察官有关
but with the new DA.
除非这两个人是同一人
Unless these two are one and the same.
丹特是一位斗士
Dent's a crusader
但我不认为他会弄脏自己的手
but I can't see him getting his hands dirty.
蝙蝠侠还比较有可能
More likely the bat.
想听建议吗？
You want advice?
无论输赢  只有和平才能结束战争
Win or lose, the only thing that ends war is peace.
和卡麦和解？
Make peace with carmine?
爸爸…
Papa...
我不知道
I don't know.
我不…
I don't...
爸爸！
Papa!
萨尔！
Sall
我听到枪声
I heard a gunshot.
你没事吧？
Are you okay?
怎么回事？
What happened?
（阿尔贝托·法尔康尼）
（挚爱的儿子）
奇怪的谈生意地点
Strange place to do business.
我想这是那群条子唯一想不到你会来的地方
Guessing it's the last spot the pigs leave you alone these days.
加班吗？
Working late?
你是怎么通过保安的？
How the hell did you get through security?
你当时就在他身边  对吗？
You were with him, right?
我必须结束这场和法尔康尼家族之间愚蠢的战争
I needed to put an end to the stupid war with the falcones.
我父亲的遗言是  我应该和敌人握手言和
My father's last words to me were that I should make peace with my enemy.
起初我以为他说的是卡麦…
At first I thought he meant carmine...
但是路易吉·马洛尼绝不会希望这么做
But Luigi maroni would have never wanted that.
那他只有可能是另外一个意思了  所以…
There's only one other thing he could have meant, so...
我来和执法者和解  谈条件
I'm here to make peace with the law. Cut a deal.
你想抓到法尔康尼  我有很多他的把柄
You want Falcone and I got plenty on him.
足以让他永远吃牢饭
Enough to put him away for good.
你的交换条件是…
In exchange for...
撤销针对我和我手下的逮捕令
Dropping all outstanding warrants against me and my men.
你想抓到法尔康尼？
You want Falcone?
条件就是这样  要不要随便你
That's the deal. Take it or leave it.
这样吧  掷到人头  我就接受
Tell you what, heads, I'll take it.
我原本以为新年的意外后  很少人会来这里
I expected a low turnout after the new year's fiasco.
-但这样真的很可悲  -我还好
- But this is really pathetic.  - Fine by me.
愈多人待在家  我工作愈轻松
The more people stay home, the easier my job gets.
说到工作变轻松  你真的逮到马洛尼了？
Speaking of jobs getting easier, is it true you got maroni?
还没结束
It's not a done deal.
我的办公室正在处理细节
My office is working out the details now.
但如果老萨尔把他跟我说的都告诉法官…
But if old sal tells a judge what he's told me...
那么可以说今天是罗马人
Let's just say today's a good day for the Roman
庆祝他所剩不多自由的好日子
to celebrate what's left of his freedom.
说曹操  曹操到
Speak of the devil.
难得看你假日在外面晃
I'm surprised to find you outdoors on a holiday.
-丹特  -法尔康尼
- Dent.  - Falcone.
其实我指的是你太太…  丹特太太
Actually, I was speaking to your wife... Mrs. dent.
别碰她
Don't touch her.
没想到你是位爱国人士  卡麦
I never took you for a patriot, carmine.
我绝对不会错过这么盛大的烟火的
I wouldn't miss fireworks like this for all the world.
晚安  丹特太太  队长
Good evening, Mrs. dent, captain.
晚安
Evening.
哈维  我跟你说  若是可以
I tell you, harv, if I could,
我今晚会安排所有警察到这里来
I'd have every cop in the city here tonight.
（高谭银行）
另一头见了
See you on the other side.
（高谭银行）
大笨蛋被敲昏了脑袋
Utter inanity proved his insanity
证明了他有多不正常
while he rattled a couple of bones.
我一直在想这件事  也许你是对的
I've been thinking about it and maybe you're right.
什么事？
Uh, about what?
生儿育女
Having kids.
退开
Stay down.
去找高登  我马上回来
Get to Gordon. I'll be back.
哈维  不  哈维！
Harvey, no. Harvey!
走开
Get out of here.
等我搞清楚这个人渣为什么要杀我再说
Not till I know why this scumbag is trying to kill me.
要是我想杀你  你早就挂了
If I was trying to kill you, you'd be dead already.
那你为什么…
Then what are you...
够了
That's enough.
有人想挑衅你  丹特
Someone's trying to provoke you, dent.
挑衅我做什么？
Into doing what?
好问题…
Good question...
起来
Get up.
“海象和木匠
"The walrus and the carpenter
一起散着步
Were walking close at hand.
他们看到大片沙滩  悲从中来
They wept like anything to see such quantities of sand.
‘如果七名女仆拿着七支拖把打扫整整半年’
'If seven maids with seven mops swept it for half a year,
海象说  ‘你觉得她们能打扫干净吗？’”
do you suppose, ' the walrus said, 'that they could get it clear?"
我很怀疑
I doubt it.
到了
There.
暂时存放点
That's the drop.
至于蝙蝠侠
As for the bat,
把他送来不是说好的一部分
delivering him wasn't part of the deal.
所以我们想对他做什么都可以
So we can do whatever we want with him.
多好玩
What fun.
一闪一闪小蝙蝠
Twinkle, twinkle little bat.
满天都是你的影…
How I wonder what you're...
你和罗马人的合作  就在今晚结束
Your business with the Roman ends tonight.
不
No.
可怜的小东西
Poor little thing.
迷你的小东西
Such a tiny little thing.
不
No.
-在下面  -什么情况？
- Down here.  - What do you got?
快跑！
Run!
动机意味着机会
Motive means opportunity.
（独家  卡拉·法尔康尼·维提）
好吧  丹特  让我说清楚
Dent. All right, let me be clear.
这个怪胎不准再骚扰我们家  不准！
This freak is done terrorizing my family. Done!
你指望我们相信一位备受尊敬的公仆…
You expect us to believe that a respected public servant...
我不懂你为什么要看那种垃圾节目
I don't know why you watch that garbage.
是真的吗？
Is it true?
你相信她的鬼话？  所以你才想离婚？
You believe this bs? Is that why you want a divorce?
我没这么说过
I never said that.
我一直说的是治疗
I have been talking about therapy.
也许离婚不是坏事  既然你无法回到他身边
Maybe divorce isn't so bad, now that you can't go back to him.
忘恩负义的贱人
Ungrateful bitch.
抱歉  我不知道我为什么这么说
I'm sorry. I don't know why I said that.
我要赶不上出庭了
I'm going to be late for court.
你又没关地下室的门了
You left the basement door open again.
我今天还没去过地下室
I haven't been in the basement today.
（牛津大学）
丹特先生？
Mr. dent?
丹特先生  你准备好继续了吗？
Mr. dent, are you ready to proceed?
呃  是的  庭上  谢谢
Uh, yes. Yes, your honor. Thank you.
杀人犯
Murderer.
什么？
What?
我问你是否准备好了  丹特先生
I asked if you're ready, Mr. dent.
是的  当然
Yes, of course.
马洛尼先生  你已经坦承十九条罪状…
Mr. maroni, you have confessed to 19 counts...
坦承
Confess.
他在干嘛…
What the hell is he...
他在这里  队长  屋顶上
He's here, captain. The roof.
检察官先生  我们都在等
Mr. district attorney, we are all waiting.
是的  抱歉  庭上
Uh, yes, yes. Sorry, your honor.
有必要到屋顶上吗？
Rooftop really necessary?
我以为你想要私人空间
I thought you'd want privacy.
哈维在法庭上快失控了
Harvey's starting to lose it down there.
我认为媒体对假日杀手的猜测  终于影响到了…
I think all this holiday speculation in the press is finally getting to...
私人空间？
Privacy?
怎么了？
Why?
你在哪里找到的？
Where'd you find them?
你不会喜欢答案的
You're not going to like it.
没错  我杀了法兰基加佐和他的兄弟蓝尼
Uh, yeah. I hit Frankie gazzo and his brother Lenny.
把他们的尸体扔进高谭河
Tossed their bodies in the Gotham river.
你正在找的聪明人都在那里面
Lots of wise guys you're looking for are in there.
也许我是因为这样才有溃疡  毕竟喝了那里的水
Maybe that's why I got an ulcer. You know, from drinking the water.
你不是依照罗马人  卡麦·法尔康尼的直接指示
And didn't you commit these murders and felonies
犯下这些谋杀和重罪吗？
under direct orders from carmine "the Roman" Falcone?
重罪？不  那家伙是圣人
Felonies? Nah, guy's a Saint.
-就是现在  -就是现在
- Now.  - Now.
你还好吧  丹特？
You okay, dent?
怎么了  胃灼热吗？
What is it, heartburn?
我很乐意分享药给你
Happy to share.
马洛尼先生  容我提醒你
Now, Mr. maroni, may I remind you that your immunity
你必须在诉讼过程诚实证言  才能取得豁免权
is contingent upon your truthful testimony during these proceedings.
我说的是事实啊  法尔康尼非常清白
And I told you the truth. Falcone is clean as a whistle.
萨尔  你在做什么？
Sal, what are you doing?
做我该做的事
What I'm told.
好吧
Okay.
庭上  监于证人…
Um, your honor, in light of the witness's...
背叛！
Double cross!
改变主意  我请求延期审理
Change of heart, I need to request a continuance.
延期审理？ 那是什么意思？ 等于放假吗？
Continuance? Uh, what is that? Like, uh, a holiday?
-什么？  -假日
- What?  - Holiday.
你知道  就像父亲节
You know, like father's day.
路易吉·马洛尼送上他的祝福
Luigi maroni sends his regards.
去吧
Go.
法警  拘留证人！
Bailiff, detain the witness!
你死定了  假日杀手！
You're dead, holiday!
听到没  丹特？  那东西连混凝土都能腐蚀！
You hear me, dent? That stuff will eat through concrete!
-哈维！  -天啊
- Harvey!  - My god.
快叫救护车！
Call an ambulance!
（假日悬案破案？）
一群白痴
Idiots.
他们以为是你
They think it's you.
你是谁？
Who are you?
你知道我是谁
You know who I am.
不  我…
No, I...
你听起来很累
You sound tired.
不如让我代劳吧？
Why not let me take the wheel?
我不知道发生了什么事
I don't know what's happening.
抱歉  没人告诉你  哈维
I'm sorry no one told you, harv.
告诉我什么？
Told me what?
你已经死了
You're dead.
我得接这通电话
I have to take this.
喂？
Yeanh.
现在？
Now?
不  时机正好
No, it's the perfect time.
医生说他几天后就没事了  别担心
The doctor says he'll be fine  in a few days. Don't worry.
天啊！
Oh, my god!
他不见了
He's gone.
封锁出口  他走不远的  走吧！
Secure the exits. He couldn't have gotten far. Let's go!
这是哪里…
Well, where is...
我猜猜  你决定还是不来了
Let me guess. You're not coming after all.
恐怕是的
Afraid not.
是啊  你不是会弄脏自己手的人
Yeah. You're not really one to get your hands dirty.
你对我一无所知
You know nothing about me.
我知道你是骗子  小偷  杀人犯
I know you're a liar, a thief, a murderer.
我是一位父亲
A father.
-胆小鬼  -再见了  丹特
- A coward.  - Goodbye, dent.
好吧
Fine.
他想跟你谈谈
He wants to talk to you.
快点
Come on.
快点！
Come on!
有没有搞错？
Really?
我不是在针对你  公事公办
It's not personal. It's business.
生日快乐  爸爸！
Happy birthday, papal!
好了  来吹蜡烛吧
All right, here we go.
很愉快的一晚  谢谢各位
What a wonderful night. Thank you.
今年不太顺利
This year has been a trying one.
虽然我们尚未全面瓦解
And while we have yet to fully dismantle
针对我们的司法邪恶机器
the vicious machine
the law has set against us,
我们依然让他们吃了鳖
you might say we put a dent in it.
敬苏菲亚法尔康尼  是我们和马洛尼和解的功臣
To Sofia Falcone, for brokering the peace with maroni.
非常感谢
Mille grazie.
还有我美丽的姊妹卡拉
And my beautiful sister, Carla.
她在哪里？
Where is she?
卡拉？
Carla?
也许还有很多电视专访要忙
Probably more TV interviews.
别这样  这些专访很有效
Now, now. Those interviews helped.
我想她的未来指日可待
I think she's got a future.
抱歉吓到你
Sorry to startle you.
你不是应该在找哈维吗？
Shouldn't you be looking for Harvey?
我问了几位伙伴  缩小了他的位置范围
I'm narrowing down his location by interviewing known associates.
几位伙…喔
Known associ... oh...
你这是在浪费时间
Well, you're wasting your time.
那个男人是一团谜  至少看起来是这样
The man's a mystery. Or so it would seem.
你有注意到他最近的行为  出现变化吗？
Did you notice any recent changes in his behavior?
情绪波动？
Mood swings?
每天都跟法尔康尼那种人打交道
Is that so strange when you deal with people
能不激动吗？
like Falcone every day?
哈维从没提过他是牛津毕业的
Harvey never mentioned he went to Oxford.
很重要吗？
Is it important?
也许吧
Maybe.
感觉你不是单纯为了公事而来
This doesn't feel like just a job for you.
是私事  怎么了吗？
It's personal. Why?
他是我朋友  他需要我帮忙
He's my friend, and he needs help.
晚餐时间到了吗？
Dinner time already?
所罗门格兰迪
"Solomon grundy,
星期一出生…
born on a Monday..."
星期二受洗  星期三结婚
"Christened on a Tuesday, married on a Wednesday,
星期四生病  星期五病危
I'll on Thursday, worse on Friday,
星期六死亡
died on Saturday."
星期日埋葬
"Buried on Sunday."
那就是他的最后
That was the end.
星期一出生
"Born on a Monday."
重生  复活
Reborn, resurrected.
就在星期一
On a Monday.
那说的是你的经历吗？
Is that what happened to you?
你死而复生吗？
Did you die and come back?
一个人能过双面生活吗？
Can a man live two lives?
星期一出生
Born on a Monday.
九月有三十天
Thirty days hath September.
但今天让你最困扰
But today's the one that troubles you the most.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
已经好几个月了
It's been months.
我很想你
I've missed you.
被攻击重伤的检察官  从医院消失
The da who was attacked and maimed before vanishing from the hospital.
嗯  他还是老样子
Hmm, he does that.
后来当晚  卡拉维提
Later that night, Carla viti,
她曾公开指控丹特是假日杀手
who'd publicly accused dent of being holiday,
在前往兄弟的生日派对途中被杀害
was killed on her way to her brother's birthday party.
我知道  真惨啊
I know. Wasn't that terrible?
我觉得她说得对
I think she was right.
你当然觉得了
Of course you do.
似乎每个紧咬丹特的人  最后都死了
It seems everyone who comes after dent winds up dead.
我们必须在哈维再杀人之前找到他
We need to find Harvey before he kills again.
你知道些什么？
What do you know?
高登和他的人每天都到这里问我同样的问题
Gordon and his men have been here day after day asking the same thing.
我把我跟队长说的告诉你吧
I'll tell you what I told the captain.
让我走出这里  我就不再杀人
Let me walk out of here and I'll stop the killing.
没什么好谈的了
We're done.
今天是劳动节
It's labor day.
如果模式不变
And, if the pattern holds,
我相信你身上有假日杀手想要的东西
I believe you have something holiday wants.
在阿特沃往北走
Head north on atwell.
-长官  监狱在南边…  -我知道在哪里
- Sir, the penitentiary is south...  - I know where it is.
这是我见过
最漫长该死的囚犯转移
This is the longest goddamn
prisoner transfer I've ever seen.
看来你们很喜欢我啊
Guess you guys
just can't get enough of me.
丹特！
Dent!
你还活着？
You're alive?
他不再是这场行动的负责人
He's no longer running this operation.
好吧
All right.
够了
That's enough.
别激动  吉姆  我不是来杀马洛尼的
Relax, Jim, I'm not here to kill maroni.
我是来感谢他给我一个全新的…面貌
I'm here to thank him for giving me a new... outlook.
噢  天啊
Oh, my god.
哈维…
Harvey...
不得不说  吉姆  你的枪正好派上用场
I have to tell you, jimbo, your gun has come in handy.
我知道你是给哈维的  但他的身体我说了算
I know it was meant for Harvey, but possession is nine-tenths.
如果你不是哈维  那你是谁？
If you're not Harvey, then, who are you?
假日杀手？
Holiday?
我们在你家地下室找到了枪枝
We found the guns in your basement.
你在我家地下室发现枪枝？
You found the guns in my basement?
当然了
Of course.
我们都知道了
We know everything.
我们只想帮助你
We just wanna take you to get help.
我认为托马斯韦恩当年
查到了什么
I think Thomas Wayne was onto something.
你用你的方式是打不倒他们的  吉姆
You can't beat 'em, jimbo, not your way.
你得先加入他们
Join 'em first.
用他们的条件击败他们
Then beat 'em on their own terms.
正面  你死定了
Heads, you die.
由你决定  哈维
It is up to you, Harvey.
你我都很清楚  那枚硬币两面都是正面
You and I know that both sides of that coin are heads.
你怎么能…
How the hell could you...
一身劲装哦  蝙蝠侠
Oh, nice outfit, bats.
我想这个小陷阱是你的主意
I suppose this little trap was your idea.
马上把枪放下！
Drop the gun, now!
不！
Nol
好了  格兰迪  快走
Come on, grundy, move your ass.
我想我们回到原点了
I think we're back to square one.
你起来得真早
Ah, you're up early.
嗯？
Hmm?
不  我刚回来
Oh, no, I just got in.
当然了  那我想你该休息了
Of course. Then I suppose it's off to bed with you.
-有什么需要帮忙的吗？  -怎么会发生这种事  阿福？
- Is there something I can help...  - How did it happen, Alfred?
他们是被迫和法尔康尼家族合作吗？
Were they forced into business with the falcones?
还是他们一心想受世人尊敬  而选择和魔鬼合作？
Or were they so set on building a legacy that they'd work with the devil himself?
你父母相信看任何事都有两种角度…
Your parents believed that there are two ways to look at everything...
看任何人也一样
And everyone.
只有两种吗？
Only two?
他们当时还年轻
They were young.
两个很棒的人  住在很险恶的环境
Two exceptionally good people living in an exceptionally bad place,
试图改善生活
trying to make it better.
但是法尔康尼呢？
But Falcone?
他们难道不知道承认他
Didn't they know that by legitimizing him,
就等于成了打造怪物的帮凶？
they were helping to make a monster?
他们做出许多艰难决定  也犯下不少错误
They made difficult choices and more than a few mistakes.
但他们愿意补偿他们
But they were willing to pay for them.
我一直告诉自己  我做的事是为了让他们自豪
I've always told myself that I'm doing what I do to honor them.
若是我做的事  其实是替他们补偿呢？
What does it mean if deep down, I'm really doing it to redeem them?
我想那意味着你父母  会为他们真正的遗产…
I think it means your parents would be proud...
深感自豪
Of their real legacy.
太荒谬了
This is absurd.
抱歉打扰了  女士  但今天是万圣节
Sorry for the inconvenience, ma'am, but it's Halloween.
丹特先生还没落网
Mr. dent is still at large.
高登队长命令我们在这待命
And captain Gordon ordered us
to be here.
所以你得跟我们困在这里了
So you're stuck with us.
你们扣留了我的车
You've blocked in my car.
我们非常乐意载你到你要去的地方
We're more than happy to drive you anywhere you need to go.
虽然你待在家里对我们来说会比较轻松
Though you'll be making our jobs a lot easier if you remain indoors.
目前没有办法得知你丈夫在哪里  或何时会出现
There's no way to know where or when your husband will show up.
我丈夫死了
My husband is dead.
抱歉  女士  但那不是事实
I'm sorry, ma'am, but that's not true.
是真的
Yes, it is.
醒醒  朱利安
Wake up, Julian.
你知道今天是什么日子
You know what today is.
是万圣节前夜…
It's all hallows' Eve...
十月的第三十一天…
The 31st day of the tenth month...
还有这个悲惨闰年的第305天
And the 305th of this miserable leap year.
还有呢？
And?
塔可星期二
Taco Tuesday.
非常好
Muy bueno.
搞什么？
“What the hell?
不给糖就捣蛋
Trick or treat.
正大光明攻击我们…
Attacking us like that out in the open...
不符合凶手侧写
It didn't fit the profile.
那就是职业杀手了
So it was a hired gun.
我们看到丹特和假日杀手同时出现在同一地点
We see dent and holiday in the same place at the same time,
这么一来  检察官就有不在场证明
and, just like that, the da's got himself an alibi.
哈维是牛津毕业的吗？
Did Harvey study at Oxford?
跟法尔康尼的儿子一样？
Like Falcone's boy?
我知道你是怎么想的  但别让哈维听到你这么说
I see where you're going but don't let Harvey hear you say it.
他是高谭大学毕业的
He's a Gotham u man.
立场坚定的夜鹰
A dyed-in-the-wool nighthawk.
别太担心了
Don't get hung up on it.
还没查证所有线索
Not every lead checks out.
我们已经有足够证据能破案了
And we already have what we need to make our case.
（哈维丹特）
很难相信那个站在这个屋顶
It's hard to believe the man who stood on this roof
和我们一起做出承诺的人
and made that promise, that bond with each of us,
会越了界
would cross the line.
你真的认为那个在后巷的人
Can you honestly say that man
跟我们认识的是同一人吗？
and the one we met in the alley were the same?
他身上有深深的伤痕…
There are deep scars there...
我指的不是他的脸
And I'm not talking about his face.
如果你觉得我们想错了  就找出证据
If you think we're wrong, find the evidence.
但现在拯救生命
But, for now, the best way to save lives,
还有拯救哈维最好的方式  就是把他带回来
including Harvey's, is to bring him in.
你知道我身边的人  都怎么称呼过去这一年吗？
Do you know what my people call this past year?
“漫长的万圣节”
The long Halloween.
我的侄子
My nephew,
我儿子  我姊妹
my son, my sister,
我半数手下
half my men.
为什么？
Why?
丹特为什么会想杀了你儿子？
Why would dent kill your son?
但愿我有机会做一个更好的父亲
I wish I had the chance to be a better father to my boy.
但我们天人永隔了
We will never see each other again.
关于这件事…
我很…
I am so...
抱歉
So sorry.
我们这种人有一个规矩
There is a rule among my kind.
不让太太牵扯其中
We leave the wives out of it.
但是丹特没照我们的规矩来
But dent does not play by our rules.
若是那样  就会有人没命
And when that happens, people die.
谁的太太？
Whose wives?
我想正义真的是盲目的
I guess justice really is blind.
爸爸
Papa.
一切都没事  苏菲亚  我只是…绊倒了
Everything is fine, Sofia. I just... stumbled.
没必要那么做
That wasn't necessary.
也许不是
Maybe not.
你打算告诉我你为什么对他们穷追不舍吗？
Are you going to tell me why you're so obsessed with them?
我一直没谢谢你那天晚上找到我  送我回家
I never thanked you for finding me and getting me home that night.
你以为我是你母亲
You thought I was your mother.
稻草人的恐惧毒素
Scarecrow's fear toxin.
你找到我的地方  正是我失去她的地方
Where you found me is where I lost her.
我甚至不知道我妈叫什么名字
I don't even know my mother's name.
但我想有人可以告诉我
But I think there's someone who can tell me.
你父亲
Your father.
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
当那一刻到来  我不确定我有那个勇气开口问
When the time comes, I'm not sure I'll have it in me to ask.
这座城市有谁的家庭是正常的吗？
Is there even such a thing as a normal family in this city?
也许没有…
Maybe not...
对我们这种人来说
For people like us.
那是什么？
What the hell is that?
该死！
Oh, shit!
所有单位  至第六街和梅森街10之33转角处
All units, 10-33 at the corner of 6th and Mason.
能出动的单位请回答
All available units respond.
不行  队长说我们不能离开  今晚不行
No, captain said we don't leave for anything, not tonight.
老爸  是告密者
Pop goes the weasel
来吧  孩子们
Keep coming, boys.
所有人都能参加这个派对
Everyone's invited to this party.
不是所有人
Not everyone.
正面
Heads.
我说的是正面！
I meant heads!
苏菲亚  好了  我没事
Sofia, please. It was nothing.
别把我当老头子看待
Stop treating me like an old man.
你不老
You're not old.
也许我的确老了
Maybe I am.
至少在这一行太老了
Too old for this business, at least.
你有…你母亲的消息吗？
Have you... heard from your mother?
她很爱你
She loves you.
她只是不喜欢这里
Just not this place.
这里就代表我
This place is me.
我知道你这么想  也许以前是这样没错
I know you think that, and maybe at one time it was.
但很多事都变了
But things have changed,
面目全非…
so much...
就在短时间内
So fast.
我不也跟他们一样改变了吗？
Haven't I changed with them?
是啊  你变了
Yes, you have.
但当你崭露头角  妈妈也还在这里的时候
But when you were coming up, when mama was here,
你绝不会想到要雇用毒藤女和稻草人这些怪胎
you wouldn't have thought to hire freaks like poison Ivy and scarecrow.
这些人…
These... people,
他们难以掌握  爸爸
they're not stable, papa.
时代变了
Times change.
老大！
Boss!
楼下出了事
Something's wrong downstairs.
警察跑了
The cops took off
我们无法联系上任何成员
and we can't get any of our guys on the comm.
马洛…
Maron...
苏菲亚  不！
Sofia, no!
来啊  你们这群混…
Come on, you mother...
苏菲亚！
Sofia
这是怎样？
What is this?
审判日
Judgment day.
我们在下水道追丢他们
We lost them in the sewers.
你说得对  那是为了分散我们的注意力
You're right. This was meant to distract us.
是啊  但分散我们的注意力干嘛？
Yeah, but distract us from what?
我真的要感谢你  卡麦
I really owe it all to you,
carmine.
你教我所有人都是有罪的…
You've taught me
that all men are guilty...
都是无辜的
And innocent.
这让正义不过就像掷硬币这么简单
Which makes justice nothing more than the flip of a coin.
结果是难以预料的
The outcome unpredictable.
也就是说…
That is, of course...
除非体制腐化  操纵对自己有利的事
Unless the system is corrupted, rigged in a man's favor.
白天是正当的生意人和慈善家
Legit businessman/philanthropist by day.
晚上是勒索犯和杀人犯
Criminal racketeer, murderer by night.
你操纵了你的事业
You've rigged every game you've ever played
和你的家族里的所有牌局
in your business and your family.
真的只要微调
It's really the most minor of adjustments,
改变一点外貌  就能决定你…
a small change of outlook that decides if you live...
是否能活下去
Or not.
你开枪啊
Just pull the fucking trigger.
你没听清楚
You haven't listened.
如果你听清楚  卡麦  你就会第一次明白
If you had, you'd understand that for the first time, carmine,
决定权并不在我
it really isn't up to me.
祝你好运
Good luck.
不！
No!
看招  你这个虚伪的小人…
En garde, you sanctimonious shit...
噢！
Ow!
南西  让打进来的人稍等
Nancy, hold all my calls.
我得干掉一个人
I have to terminate someone.
哈维  住手！
Harvey, don't!
终于只剩下你和我了
Alone at last.
让我帮你解脱吧
Now let's get you out of all this.
退后
Stay back.
哈维
Harvey.
你不需要这么做
You don't have to do this.
哈维  哈维  哈维
Harvey, Harvey, Harvey.
你看不出来我改头换面了吗  蝙蝠侠？
Can't you see I'm a new man, bats?
我终于觉醒了
I'm finally awake.
不像哈维丹特
And unlike Harvey dent,
我不用对复仇这种没用的动机负责
I'm not beholden to petty motives like revenge,
或是糟糕的升职
or worse, career advancement.
我的重担已经卸下
A weight has been lifted.
我不需要再决定谁无罪和谁有罪
I don't have to decide who's innocent and who's guilty anymore.
我只需要…执行
All I have to do... is execute.
-有罪  -不！
- Guilty.  - No!
不！
No!
爸爸
Papa.
苏菲亚  不！
Sofia, no!
只有两颗子弹
Two bullets only.
抱歉了  美女
Sorry, gorgeous.
不不不不不
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
苏菲亚
Sofia.
我…我撑不住了
I can't... I can't hold on.
露易莎？
Louisa?
Louisa.
赛琳娜
Selina.
赛琳娜？
Selina?
我帮你
Let me help you.
不
No.
种什么因  得什么果
All we get is all we take.
你还是这么认为吗？
Do you still believe?
对
Yes.
依然如此
I do.
很好
Good.
-哈维？
-不再是了
- Harvey?
- Not anymore.
我必须这么做
It had to be done.
你永远无法说服我
You will never convince me of that.
以后不会再有收贿的法官
There won't be any judges to be bribed.
不会再有消失的证人
No witnesses to disappear.
罗马人死了  是双面人杀了他
The Roman is dead and two-face killed him.
漫长的万圣节…
The long Halloween...
已经结束了
Is over.
我们会帮助你
We'll get you help.
你们接下来才需要帮助
You're the ones who're gonna need help from now on.
哈维…
Harvey...
双面人…
Two-face...
随便吧
Whatever.
你背叛了你所有的信念
You betrayed everything you believe in.
并不是所有
Not everything.
逮捕我吧  吉姆
Arrest me, jimbo.
是我干的
I'm responsible.
不止法尔康尼  还有其他假日杀手犯下的案子
Not just for Falcone but all the holiday killings.
我必须面对审判
I have to face judgment.
代价
The cost.
我们一年前在这里立下承诺
The promise we made right here, one year ago,
要扳倒罗马人  结果…
to take down the Roman. In the end...
这么做值得吗？
Was it worth it?
他是在问好人是否赢了
He's asking if the good guys won.
是的  好人赢了
Yes, the good guys won.
但我们要过很久之后才知道
这么做值不值得
But we won't know for a very long time
if it was worth it.
（阿卡姆精神病院）
吉尔达
Gilda.
必须这么做
It had to be done.
你很清楚
You know that.
就跟你早就知道哈维从没去过牛津大学念书一样
The same way you knew Harvey never went to Oxford.
是我
That was me.
嗯…
Well...
我和…
Me and...
阿尔贝托法尔康尼
Alberto Falcone.
你可以看到我们当时深爱彼此
If you could see how in love we were then.
我怀孕了
I was pregnant.
他没有半点犹豫
He didn't hesitate.
我们当天就结婚了
We were married that same day.
他是罗马人帝国的继承人
He was heir to the Roman empire.
他父亲绝不欢迎
And his father could never welcome into the family
婚前怀的小孩进入家族
a child conceived out of wedlock.
我试图对抗
I tried to fight.
但面对高谭市的教父  我有什么机会？
But what chance did I have opposite the godfather of Gotham?
在无视我的意愿下…
Against my will...
我们的婚约取消  而我们的孩子…
Our marriage was annulled and our child...
从我的子宫夺走
Ripped from my womb.
他们对我做的事…
What they did to me...
他们所采取的方式…
The way it was done...
让我整个崩溃了
Left me broken.
你曾想复仇
You wanted revenge.
我想要的是伸张正义
I wanted justice.
我来到高谭市  嫁给了
I came to Gotham and married the man
我认为最有可能替我伸张正义的人
I thought had the best chance of delivering it.
哈维和我实在是太相似了
Oh, Harvey and I were so much alike.
只是他的内心还没被整个剖开
Only what was inside him hadn't yet been ripped out.
这一点…很有用
That was... useful.
而且…
And...
一度也很有趣
Even fun for a time.
但他后来变得很忙  对抗他自己的敌人
But then he became so busy wrestling his own demon,
我则独自一人  扳倒我自己的敌人
I was left to take down mine all by myself.
一次假日
One holiday,
夺取一个家人
one twisted family snapshot at a time.
我对罗马人  或他儿子
I have no regrets about what I did to the Roman,
或是那个罪恶家族里的其他人所做的事
or his son,
完全不后悔
or anyone else in that godforsaken family.
但是哈维…
But Harvey...
到最后  我爱上了他
In the end, I loved him.
但不是全部的他
But not all of him.
所以…
So...
你要逮捕我  还是站在那里评判我？
Are you going to take me away or just stand there in judgment?
我需要知道  假日杀手已经收手了
I need to know that holiday is done.
不是收手…
Not done...
而是结束了
Finished.
我不禁想…  他从多久前就知道我的事了？
I wonder... How long did he know about me?
你是这样想通的吗？
Is that how you figured it out?
哈维有向你透露消息吗？
Did Harvey tip you off?
他并没有供出你
He didn't give you up.
据我所知没有
Not knowingly.
但马洛尼被杀害后
But after maroni was killed,
从他护航假日杀手的方式  他一定从那时就知道了
the way he protected holiday, he must have known then.
他是我的朋友
He was my friend.
他信任我
He believed in me.
我应该拯救他的
I should have saved him.
你现在打算怎么做？
What will you do now?
跟高登说？
Tell Gordon?
阿福？
Alfred.
真的假的？
Really?
我知道很晚了  少爷  但你永远预料不到
I know it's late, sir, but you never know.
跟晚不晚没关系  不会有人来跟我们讨糖吃
It doesn't matter how late it is. We don't get trick-or-treaters.
并非所有高谭市的家庭都跟你一样坚持
Not all Gotham families share your obstinate hope.
必须有更多好人试图改善这个世界
It's going to take a lot more good people trying to make things better
才能看到真正的改变
before we see real change.
你说了算  少爷
If you say so, sir.
你犯错的时候真可爱
You're cute when you're wrong.
不给糖  就捣蛋
Trick or treat.
是找你的  少爷
It's for you, sir.